Let us now understand how .NET apps are run in Docker.
First a Docker container is created.
Next we install an operating system like Windows, Linux, or Mac OS in this container.
Then in this OS we install .NET runtime or SDK.
Next we install a web server like
Apache, Engine X, etc.
Finally a .NET app will run from inside this container.
Since the app has all deleted resources or dependencies like OS.NET runtime as pk web servers
like Engine X.
So this .NET app is ready to run from inside the Docker container.
Let us understand the working from a real world example.
The boy is opening an ASP.NET Core website on his browser.
First a browser will make an HTTP request to the Engine X web server.
Engine X web server will forward this request to cluster web server.
Note that Engine X is working as a reverse proxy in this case.
Crestale is hosting the .NET web site.
It forwards the request to the web site.
The web site in turn sends back the response to Crestale.
And now Crestale forwards the request to Engine X web server.
Finally, Engine X sends the response to the boy's browser.
The browser will show the web site.
This whole thing, the Engine X the cluster, the .NET app, is hosted on a Docker container.
Docker is super fast and easy.
Think about installing Windows 11 with .NET SDK on your PC.
It will take no less than one hour of your time.
But in Docker you can install both these things in just 20 to 30 seconds only.
You just have to run the Docker commands and Docker will do the heavy lifting for you.
The Docker commands will tell Docker engine what type of Docker container you need.
Along with the software needed on the container.
This whole process is extremely fast.
Docker will provide the container running in a matter of seconds.
Create containers of different .NET versions.
For example, a container can be running on Windows along with .NET version 10.
Second container can be running on Linux with .NET 8.0.
Third container can be running on Linux with .NET version 9 along with Node.js and PHP.
These all three containers can run at the same time from the host operating system.
Docker provides these containers all the resources they need for the need.
These includes, required software, like Linux, .NET, Node.js and PHP installed on these
containers, note that there is no need to install Linux, Node.js .NET or PHP on the host
machine which is our PC as these are running from inside the containers.
Benefits of Docker fast and easy continuous delivery of apps.
Docker is great for continuous integration and continuous delivery of software development.
This is known as CI/CD.
Developers and testers working in a project can share their work using Docker containers.
This developer creates code for a .NET app and pushes the whole app on a Docker container.
The tester will use the container to test the code and will provide the bug list.
This means that Docker container, both the developer and tester are working together.
Once the bug list is resolved, the new .NET app is deployed to the production.
It is not necessary for the developers and testers to remain side by side sitting at the
same office that testers can be anywhere on the world.
They just need to test the app from Docker containers.
In this way, Docker provides very fast and consistent delivery of apps.
Responsive development and scaling of apps with Docker.
For example, we have a .NET website and we noticed a traffic to the website has increased
by 100%.
We can increase the Docker containers hosting the website in order to fulfill the new demands.
Earlier, we were hosting the website from 10 containers.
In the same way, we can scale down the app by reducing the containers, thus reducing
the hosting charges of our website, reducing the cost of development of apps when we use
Docker, a small startup has a small team of developers and testers and they do not have
lots of funds to create infrastructure so they can run all the needful apps from the
Docker containers.
These apps are SQL Server, MySQL, Redis.NET, Node.js, Apache and others.
As reducing the infrastructure cost of the company also, they do not have to shed more
money on buying their license fees when they are running the apps from the Docker containers.